You silly twerp, take it easy.
小傻子 别着急啊
Next, welcome
接下来有请
any two debaters
双方任意辩手
to have a one-to-one debate.
进行一对一攻辩
Welcome.
有请
Hello, my fellow debater.
对方辩友你好
Hello.
你好
Can I ask you
请问他律
if heteronomy is ubiquitous?
是无处不在的吗
Is there a vacuum in heteronomy?
他律有没有真空地带
Definitely.
有
So,
所以
self-discipline plays a role in
自律在他律的
the vacuum of heteronomy.
真空地带起作用
Does that demonstrate that
这是否正说明
self-discipline is only a supplement to heteronomy?
自律只是他律的补充呢
He's switching the relation of elements with keywords.
用关键词偷换要素关系
Is supplement not important?
补充不重要吗
One reverses an overwhelming adverse situation
扶大厦于将倾
like saving a gigantic building from its collapse at the last critical moment.
挽狂澜于既倒
Is it a supplement?
算不算一种补充呢
Why is
为什么作为
self-discipline, which is an important supplement
重要补充部分的自律
not
反而没有
more important than heteronomy which is not needed.
缺席的他律重要呢
Because the supplement is not the subject.
因为补充不是主体
What we advocate is that
我方倡导的是
in a society with a good system,
在制度完善的社会下
heteronomy can
他律可以
guide all your actions.
指导你的一切行为
Everyone and everything
每一个人每一件事
are guided by heteronomy.
都被他律所指导
Without exception.
无一例外
But my fellow debtor
可对方辩友
advocated to prioritize the self-discipline.
主张自律优先
Do you want us to go back to
难道是想让我们回到
the chaotic and disordered
混乱无序的
dark forest?
黑暗森林中吗
The chaos and disorder of the dark forest
黑暗森林的混乱无序
is precisely
恰恰是因为
the consequence of
缺少自律
the lack of self-discipline.
所导致的后果啊
I'm afraid this stems from
这恐怕源于
the fact that we both
我们双方对于
have different judgments about human nature.
人性的判断不同
Can I ask my fellow debater another question?
再请问对方辩友
As the saying goes, it's difficult to follow the path of virtue
所谓从善如登
but easy to succumb to vice.
从恶如崩
Is self-discipline
自律是不是
more difficult to adhere to than heteronomy?
相比于他律更难坚持
Doesn't difficulty mean
困难不正意味着
it's important?
重要吗
For example, I
好比我
got 130 points in the Chinese exam
语文考一百三十分
while only 60 points in math.
数学只考六十分
For me, is it
学好数学
more important
是不是对我来说
to learn math well?
更重要呢
Is the shortcoming itself more important?
是短板本身更重要
Or is it more important to make up for the shortcoming?
还是补齐短板更重要
For my fellow debater,
对于对方辩友而言
what really matters
真正重要的
should be how to
应该是如何
improve the math performance
提高数学成绩
rather than the math itself.
而不是数学本身吧
Next, welcome
下面有请
any two debaters
双方任意辩手
to make a summary
对上述质询
of the above-mentioned questioning session.
攻辩环节进行小结
The time is three minutes.
时间为三分钟
First, let's welcome the positive side.
那么首先有请正方
Dango
团子
Do you know that?
你明白吗
When everyone performed
当大家都搞得
seamlessly
天衣无缝
and meticulously,
精雕细琢时
my suggestion is to improvise.
我劝你即席
In this way,
如此一来
your plain language,
你平实的用语
occasional stammering,
偶尔的结巴
and incoherent words because of excitement,
激动下的词不达意
will instead...
反而
They will all be weapons.
一样一样都是武器
Thank you, chief judge.
谢谢主席
Hello, everyone.
大家好
my fellow debater
对方辩友
thinks the criterion for judging importance
对重要的判断标准
is whether it is conducive to growth.
是有利于成长
But what is growth?
可什么是成长
Under heteronomy,
在他律之下
studying hard to get into a prestigious school
刻苦读书 考上名校
is indeed a kind of growth.
确实是一种成长
Under heteronomy,
那在他律之下
even your major
连自己的专业
has to be decided by others.
都要别人做主
Is it a kind of growth?
是一种成长吗
When we want to be free,
当我们想要自由
but cannot control ourselves,
又管不好自己
Time and time again, we have to pay
一次次付出
a painful price.
惨痛的代价
Is it
这到底又算不算
a kind of growth?
是一种成长呢
So, what is the growth?
所以什么才是成长啊
Can't we
难道我们怎么长大
decide
我们自己都
how we grow up?
不能做主吗
When I first entered college,
初次进入大学
I spent all night with my friends,
我跟朋友一起通宵
having beer and skittles together.
一起吃喝玩乐
For the first time ever, I tasted
我第一次尝到
the joy of mastering my own affairs.
当家做主的快乐
I would like to
我恨不得把自己
take back
压抑的十几年来
all the freedom
所有的自由
that was suppressed for more than ten years.
全部夺回来
I will buy beautiful skirts.
我要好看的裙子
They are cheap when they are on sale on the shopping festival.
购物节打折很便宜啊
I will eat all
我要吃遍
the delicious food around.
周边的好吃的
A few dozen dollars a meal
几十块钱一顿
is a good deal.
很划算呀
I have worked hard for more than a decade.
辛苦了十几年
I want to dawdle in bed and skip a class.
我要赖床逃次课
It's no big deal.
没什么大不了的
It doesn't cost much each time.
每次也没花多少钱
I'm really not a person who likes wasting.
我真的不算浪费的
The single-plank bridge of the college entrance examination
高考的独木桥
has been crossed by me.
都过来了
Skipping one or two classes
我逃一两次课
will have no influence on my excellence.
也耽误不了我的优秀
How can I possibly
我怎么可能
not manage my own
管不好我自己的
life?
人生呢
But one day,
直到有一天
The balance on the card becomes negative.
卡里的余额变成负数
The public list of retakes
重修的公示名单上
contains my name.
写着我的名字
How could that happen?
这怎么可能
Where is my money?
钱到底花在哪里了
Where is my time?
时间到底去了哪儿
What shall I do?
我该怎么办
I was afraid.
我害怕
I was afraid to mention it to my parents.
我害怕向父母提起
I was afraid to lose
我害怕失去
the freedom that I just obtained.
刚刚获得的自由
I was afraid of becoming
我害怕重新成为那个
the person who lives
生活在别人
in the shadow of others again.
阴影之下的人
I started to borrow money from everywhere.
我开始四处借钱
I started to use online loans.
开始使用网贷
I started to hire someone to deal with the attendance.
开始花钱找人点名
I even started to
甚至开始在
buy assignments online.
网上买作业
But,
但是
When the phone rings of demanding payments of the debts,
当催债的电话响起
when my friends became
当朋友都成了
my debtors,
我的债主
when the
当曾经的
merit student
那个三好学生
now was at the bottom of the class,
如今却是全班垫底时
I have found that
我才发现
without knowing it,
在毫不自知的情况下
I had already indulged
我早已放纵
and lost my bottom line.
和丢掉了自己的底线
How I wish
我多么希望
there was a heteronomy
有一个对方口中的
put forward by my fellow debaters
他律
to discipline me,
能够来约束我
and to warn me.
警醒我
But after thinking over it,
可是仔细一想
heteronomy has never left me.
他律从未离开过我啊
It is
它是我们
a nag in our ears,
耳畔的唠唠叨叨
a cliché, and groundless worries or anxieties.
老生常谈 杞人忧天
It is like
是我们口中的
I know that.
我知道了
Knock it off. Don't you feel fidget?
你别说了 你烦不烦
Think about that.
你们看
We can always
我们总能把
leave the heteronomy we don't like
不喜欢的他律
isolated from
隔离在自己的
our own lives.
生活之外
Heteronomy can
他律永远
never dominate our lives.
无法主宰我们的人生
Only we
只有我们
are the masters of our own lives.
自己才是生活的主人
Should we
到底是要像
seek the help and shelter
对方辩友那样
of heteronomy
寻求他律的
like my fellow debaters,
帮助和庇护
or should we
还是拿出
behave like a master?
一个主人该有的样子
You have the right to choose.
你们自己选
Thank you.
谢谢
Well done, Dango.
团子好样的
The summary is done.
小结搞定
Next,
接下来
the winner and loser
胜负手
will be decided in the free debate.
就看自由辩论了
Next,
接下来
it's the free debate.
进入自由辩论环节
First,
首先由
any debater of the positive side will stand up,
正方任意辩手起立
and sit down after the speech.
发言结束后坐下
Then, any debater of the opposing side
由反方任意辩手
will stand up to give us a speech.
起立发言
The two sides alternate.
双方交替进行
When the time of one side runs out,
一方时间用尽
the other side can continue to speak.
另一方可继续发言
Four minutes each.
分别计时四分钟
Welcome.
有请
Since heteronomy
既然他律
ultimately works only
最终都要通过自律
through self-discipline,
才能起作用
why is
那为什么反而是
heteronomy more important?
他律更重要的呢
Doesn't any restraint
任何约束不都要通过
work through us?
我们自身起作用吗
Slaves were
奴隶被鞭子
driven to labor by whips.
驱赶着劳动
But the feet
可是脚长在
are themselves.
他们自己身上
According to what you said,
按照您的说法
can this be called self-discipline?
难道这也能叫自律吗
The Qing Dynasty has fallen
大清都亡了
for more than a century.
一百多年了
Can you stop living
对方辩友您就别活在
in the slave society of
两千多年前
more than 2,000 years ago?
的奴隶社会了行吗
Today we
今天的我们
all need to
每个人都需要
be responsible for ourselves,
对自己负责
and have the ability to discipline ourselves,
都要有自律的能力
don't we?
不是吗
Heteronomy is irresponsible?
他律就是不负责吗
My fellow debater claimed that if you abandon self-discipline,
对方辩友说放弃自律
the world will abandon you.
世界就会放弃你
Is that true?
真的是这样吗
Then my fellow debater
那对方辩友
might as well go to prison
不妨去监狱里
and ask
问问那些放弃
the lawbreakers who have abandoned self-discipline.
自律的不法分子
Did the law
法律
abandon him or not?
到底有没有放弃他
Your side have admitted that
您方自己也承认了
there is a vacuum
他律也有管不到的
where heteronomy cannot manage.
真空地带
Parents will grow old.
父母会老去
Families will get separated.
亲人会离散
When you are in college,
您大学的时候
you do not develop
都不培养
self-discipline.
自律的能力
When will you develop it?
什么时候培养呢
A small tree is not a seedling unless it is trimmed.
小树不修不成苗
Nothing can be accomplished without norms or standards.
没有规矩就不成方圆
Heteronomy can
他律完全可以
be used to develop self-discipline.
用来培养自律嘛
I would like to ask my fellow debaters.
再请问对方辩友了
Is the law more
法律是不是管束效果
effective than self-discipline?
要比自律强呢
I think when you are in college,
我觉得在大学时期
if you don't develop
不好好培养自己
the self-discipline,
的自律能力的话
you may really
将来你可能真的
need the law
需要法律
to control you in the future.
来好好管管你
Zengzi said that
曾子说
I do self-inspection on three aspects every day.
吾日三省吾身
Confucius also said that
孔子也曾说
if you cannot restrain yourself,
不能正其身
how to restrain others?
如正人何
Confucianism emphasizes being strict with yourself.
儒家强调严于律己
Does that demonstrate that
这不正说明
self-discipline is more important?
自律更重要吗
The word "inspection" in the sentence "do self-inspection on three aspects"
三省吾身的省字
means reflection.
是反思的意思
Reflection and self-discipline
反思和自律
are not the same things.
不能混为一谈
Confucius emphasized the Chou Rituals throughout his life.
孔子一生强调周礼
Doesn't this emphasize
这不正是强调了
the importance of the ceremonial system
礼法制度
as heteronomy?
作为他律的重要性吗
Wrong.
错
What Confucius emphasizes is
孔子强调的是
to restrain ourselves and restore the rites.
克己复礼
Do not speak what is contrary to propriety.
所谓非礼勿言
Do not look at what is contrary to propriety.
非礼勿视
Do not listen to what is contrary to propriety.
非礼勿听
Is this kind of self-restraint
这种克己
a kind of self-discipline?
算不算一种自律呢
Chinese people advocate self-supervision.
中国人讲君子慎独
Is it a kind of self-discipline?
是不是自律
Self-supervision is not that easy.
慎独谈何容易
Otherwise, how can there be so many
不然怎么会有那么多
idle villains?
闲居不善的小人呢
Does this prove that
这不正说明了
self-discipline is difficult
自律很难
and inefficient?
效用很低吗
Leave the efficiency alone.
不管效用
In the adulthood,
成年人的生活中
is self-discipline
是不是自律
more commonly used?
更常用呢
Not exactly.
不确切
We can say that self-discipline
可以说自律的
accounts for a larger proportion.
占比更重
Fine.
好的
We admit that.
这个我方可以承认
Isn't the one with a larger proportion
占比更重的
more important?
难道不是更重要吗
The ass in the human body
人体中屁股
is heavier
比脑袋的体重
than the head.
要占比的更重
Does that mean that
难道屁股比脑袋
the ass is more important than the head?
更重要吗
It seems that the better one can be clearly found out.
看上去都有胜负
But unknowingly,
可不知不觉中
they have admitted
已经承认了
many small arguments of the other side.
对方很多小论点
So, you think
所以您方认为
children more need self-discipline,
孩子更需要的是自律
while adults more need heteronomy, right?
而大人更需要他律了
So what?
那又如何呢
Why do we
那为什么我们
hope the adults
会对大人
more self-disciplined,
要求得更有自制力
while have few demands
而对孩子们
for the children?
不会要求太多呢
According to your logic,
按照您方的逻辑
we should ask
我们应该要求
children to be more self-controlled,
孩子们更有自制力
and adults should
而大人应该像
be arranged
幼儿园的
like children
小朋友一样
in the
被安排得
kindergarten.
明明白白的呀
Isn't it?
不是吗
Because if the
因为更具行动力的
adults with a strong action
成年人
lack self-control
自制力不足
can cause more harm.
会造成更大的伤害
So, we
所以我们
can't just chant the slogan.
不能空喊口号
We should utilize heteronomy
而要用他律
to practically help them
实际地帮他们
to solve the problems.
解决问题
Is that wrong?
这有什么错呢
They are too good at
他们太善于
using disguised replacement of concept
用偷换概念了
to make the logic confused.
来混淆逻辑了
We are always in
我们一直在
the rhythm of the other side.
对方的节奏中
Even if they react fast,
就算反应再快
they still can't counter-attack in time.
也无法及时反攻
I am the master of my youth.
我的青春我做主
Why should I
请问为什么要
deliver my freedom to others?
把自由交给他人呢
Freedom?
自由
How many sins are made in this name?
多少罪恶假汝之名
Not to mention that heteronomy is just a restraint
更何况他律只是约束
other than a master.
还不是做主
Who can live without some constraints?
谁活着还不受点约束
The emperor has to
皇帝还得
get up early to deal with the national affairs.
每天早起上朝呢
He cannot lie in.
连懒觉都没的睡
The emperors are different.
皇帝也有不一样的
Emperor Wu of the Han dynasty can certainly
汉武帝当然可以
make his own decisions.
自己做主
But Liu Xie, Emperor Xian of the Han dynasty
但是汉献帝刘协
is different.
就不一样了吧
He's digressing from the point.
跑偏啦
He is confused again.
这家伙又上头了
The example of my fellow debater
对方辩友这个例子
is interesting.
举得很有趣
Self-disciplined Emperor Wu
自律的武帝
finally
最终还是
was militaristic.
走向了穷兵黩武
His country was almost ruined.
差点连江山都毁了
It can be concluded that without heteronomy,
可见缺少了他律
the consequence is serious.
后果有多么地严重
You are wrong.
错了
Emperor Wu's mistakes in his later years
武帝晚年的过失
were precisely the result of
恰恰是不自律
the lack of self-discipline.
造成的后果
But he reflected on himself.
但他幡然自省
He issued the edict on the crime of Luntai,
发布轮台罪己诏
and no longer honored military but to advocate peace.
不再尚功而守文
Because of self-discipline, he made his country
用自律将天下
prosperous again.
重新拉回了正轨
This is the role of self-discipline.
这是自律的作用啊
But Emperor Wu regretted too late.
可是武帝悔之已晚
Tens of thousands of people died in the Witchcraft Rebellion.
巫蛊之乱死了上万人
The treasury is empty,
国库空虚
and people are rioting and unsettled.
民间暴动不安
On the contrary, Emperor Taizong of the Tang dynasty
反观唐太宗有
had the admonisher, Wei Zheng.
谏官魏征
Taking the human as the mirror can understand the gains and losses.
以人为镜可明得失
Heteronomy
他律可是
brought him
给他带来了
the Excellent Governance during the Zhenguan Times.
贞观之治啊
It seems that
明明感觉
the opposing side is not correct.
反方说得不对
But it feels that
但是感觉又
what they said makes sense.
很有道理的样子
Me too.
我也是
I think
我明明觉得
the positive side is true.
正方才是真理啊
Our arguments
我们的论点
were fixed limitedly.
修补得太有限了
It can be concluded that
只能说
the gap is narrowing.
拉小了双方差距
If we want to win...
如果想赢
Now, it's the last session
现在是本场比赛的
of the contest,
最后一个环节
the concluding speech session.
总结陈词环节
So, let's welcome
那么我们首先
any debaters of the opposing side
有请反方任意辩手
to make a concluding speech.
进行总结陈词
The time is three minutes.
时间为三分钟
Welcome.
有请
Hello, everyone.
大家好
The opinions of my fellow debaters
今天对方辩友
are too simple.
的观点很简单
They think that it's difficult to be self-disciplined.
他们觉得自律太难了
To be self-disciplined
培养自律的能力
needs more efforts,
需要付出更多的努力
more time,
更多的时间
and more energy.
更多的精力
So, they told us
所以告诉我们
to pay attention to self-discipline.
一定要重视自律
Self-discipline is more important.
自律更重要
We don't consider that they
先不说他们把
take the difficulty
困难程度
as importance.
等同于重要性
There is a
这中间存在
large logic problem.
多么大的逻辑问题
Let's go back to the point.
我们回到这个观点
Have you
大家有没有
thought about
认真地想过
self-discipline is really that difficult?
自律真的有那么难吗
Our leader told me that
我方一辩告诉我说
She was naughty when she was young.
说她小的时候很淘气
She didn't often wash her hands
经常不洗手
before eating.
就抓东西吃
Fortunately, the baby-sitter restrained her strictly.
幸亏阿姨管得严
Under the threat of the baby-sitter,
才在阿姨的威胁下
she developed a healthy and good habit.
养成了健康的好习惯
So, if you lack self-discipline,
所以自律的能力差
letting parents and teachers
就先让父母和老师
restrain us more.
多管管我们
Gradually,
然后慢慢地
and naturally,
自然而然地
the good habit will be formed.
良好的习惯就会形成
Self-discipline
自律的能力
will be developed as well.
也就培养出来了
Let me think about one question.
我们大家想一下
From childhood to adulthood,
从小到大
which ability of us
我们哪一项能力
is not
不是这么
developed like this?
培养出来的呢
We need to brush teeth after getting up.
早起要刷牙
We need to take a bath at night.
晚上要洗澡
Don't gobble up your food.
吃饭不要狼吞虎咽
We need to study step by step.
学习要按部就班
The word is learned one by one.
一个字一个字地认
The problem is calculated one by one.
一道题一道题地算
At first, which of these
这些在最初
is not forced to do
哪个不是父母和老师
by parents and teachers?
逼着我们做的呢
But now,
而现在
which one does not
哪一项没有变成
become the self-discipline of us?
我们的自律呢
After entering the college,
进入大学
we have become
我们都已经成为
adults in the legal sense.
法律意义上的成年人
The difference of us
今天我们双方
is that
不同就在于
we think that
我方认为
we have not been prepared yet.
我们还没有准备好
We still need
我们仍然需要
to have the help of the heteronomy
在他律的帮助下
to avoid making mistakes,
避免行差踏错
and strive to
努力在将来
become a better person.
成为一个更好的人
While my fellow debaters
而对方辩友
is obviously not that sober.
显然没有那么清醒
They think that
他们觉得
we have grown up.
我们好不容易长大了
I don't want to be in charge.
我才不要别人管
I can be in charge of myself.
我能管好我自己
Stop dreaming.
别做梦了
Two months ago,
两个月前
you were doing exercises at Mao Tanchang School.
你还在毛坦厂刷题
What makes
凭什么两个月之后
you think
你就觉得
you can manage yourself after two months?
你能管好你自己
There are many students with high scores
高分录取的同学
who
四年过后
do not receive a diploma
拿不到毕业证的
after four years.
比比皆是
There are high-caliber students from Tsinghua University and Peking University
清华 北大的高才生
who
因为没有
are discouraged every year
自制力而被劝退的
because of their lack of self-control.
年年都有
Why can't we
我们为什么
recognize ourselves?
不能认清我们自己
put down the proud
放下这份高傲
and greed of indulgence
和对放纵的贪婪
to admit that
去承认
we still don't have
我们还没有
enough ability
足够的能力
to be in charge of ourselves,
管好我们自己
and to admit that we still need
去承认我们仍然需要
the restraint and help of heteronomy?
他律的约束和帮助
We can then use the restraint
然后利用这份约束
and the help
利用这份帮助
to embrace the heteronomy
去接纳
instead of excluding it, can't we?
而不是排斥他律呢
Maybe ten years later,
也许十年过后
when we recollecting today,
等我们回首今日
it will also be like looking back on
也会像今日回首
our high school days today.
我们中学时代那样
We will find that the nagging parents,
发现唠叨的父母
strict teachers,
严厉的老师
harsh school regulations,
苛刻的校规
and Mr. Zhang at the gate
以及在门口
who was catching the late students
抓迟到的张大爷
were really helping you.
真的都是为了你好
Thank you.
谢谢
Clearly organized. Explicit values.
条理清晰 价值明确
He's so great.
真的好厉害
He's excellent.
好厉害哦
How wonderful!
太牛了吧
Just now the high level of
刚才这段结辩
this closing argument
水平之高
cannot be pulled back
不是团子能
by Dango.
拉得回来的
And Dango
而且团子本来
is the third debater.
就是做三辩的
Her ability of summarizing is not enough.
总结能力不行
The summary just now
刚才的小结
is her best performance.
已经是她的极限了
Now, welcome the fourth debater of the positive side
下面有请正方四辩
to make a concluding speech.
做总结陈词
Now, the result of the contest
现在比赛的结果
is on my hand.
已经在我的手上了
Next, I announce
下面我宣布
the winner of the contest is
本场比赛的获胜方为
the opposing side. Congratulations!
反方 恭喜他们
Meanwhile, congratulations to
同时也让我们恭喜
Nan Bei, the second debater of the positive side.
正方二辩南北同学
He gains the
获得本次
best debater
迎新杯辩论赛
in the Welcome Cup Debate Contest.
全程最佳辩手称号
Good job!
表现不错啊
You are better than in high school.
比高中那会儿强点
Well. I know you are great.
行了 知道你厉害
You don't need to show off on purpose.
不用特意过来显摆
Please go away.
你走吧
I just want to give you some advice.
就是提点你一下
I'm your senior.
当学姐的
I must care about my junior.
总不能不关心学妹吧
Keep practicing.
接着练吧
You can play to this extent.
能打到这个程度
It's your best.
也算是尽力了
I don't know whether you are praising me
我不知道你是夸我呢
or belittling me.
还是损我呢
But it's impossible for me to forgive you.
但我不可能原谅你
The summary was good.
小结挺精彩的
It's enough.
好了
Don't be sad.
不要难过了
There is a lot of fun
大学生活
in college.
好玩的多了去了
You can have time
这样你们不就有时间
to play, right?
可以耍起来了吗
Actually, you
其实大家这次
did a good job.
都发挥得挺好的
Right.
是啊
You did a good job.
发挥的不挺好的吗
This is called ups and downs.
这就叫大起大落嘛
It's exciting to have ups and downs.
大起大落才刺激呀
Without a fiasco,
没有经过惨败
how can it be called youth?
怎么能叫青春呢
You are not so miserable.
也不怎么惨的
You are not miserable.
不 不惨
It's a narrow defeat.
惜败 惜败
I will invite you to have a meal this weekend.
周末我请大家吃饭
Hello, who is speaking?
喂 哪位啊
I'm Qiu Lingyan.
我是秋凌烟
We found a box of comic books
我们在训练教室
in our training classroom.
找到一箱漫画书
Your agent couch said that
你们代理教练说
it's yours.
是你的
He lets me contact with you.
让我联系你来拿
Well.
哦
You leave them there.
那你先放那儿吧
I will go to fetch them.
我一会儿就去拿
I got to have a class.
我现在要去上课
So, I throw them at the door.
就给你扔门口了
How could you do that?
你这个人怎么这样
You put them at the door.
你放门口
What if others
万一被别人
take them away?
拿走怎么办
Those are signed limited edition.
那可是签名限量版
Hello.
喂
You go to the class.
你上课去
Is Liu Yanze there?
刘彦泽在不在啊
Alas!
哎哟
What a coincidence!
这么巧啊
You have a good taste.
还挺有品位
Give them to me.
给我吧
I have heard of the matter about your team.
你们队事我听说了
Are you okay?
你没事吧
That's it.
就那样吧
I would have wanted to drink to eliminate my sadness
本来想借酒消愁
and be drunk for three days.
宿醉个三天三夜的
But When I saw Xiaoyu,
但我看小鱼的状态
I thought that I would better be strong.
想想还是撑一撑吧
So does Nan Bei.
南北也是
After being defeated by Liu Yanze,
输给刘彦泽
he is dispirited, right?
他整个人都蔫了吧
He's recovering from
还在创伤应激症
the post-traumatic stress disorder.
恢复中呢
I find there are two types of people
我发现这
who
一般受打击的人
suffer shocks.
分两种
The first one is like him.
一种就是他这样
He doesn't move at the dormitory.
每天一动不动在寝室
But he finds a new hobby.
倒是发现了个新爱好
Photograph.
摄影
Isn't that good?
这不挺好的吗
He will move when taking photos.
拍照也能动动啊
Time-lapse photography.
延时摄影
He only takes one picture one night.
一晚上拍一张那种
He doesn't move all the night, right?
一晚上都不动啊
He also moves.
也动
He moves every two hours.
俩小时一动吧
He's sick badly.
那是病得不轻
Does Xiaoyu belong to his type?
小鱼和他一样吗
I think she belongs to
我觉得她属于
the other type.
另外一种
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Are you okay?
你没事吧
I have nothing wrong.
我能有什么事啊
The dopamine produced by labor
劳动产生的多巴胺
fills my body.
充满了我的身体
I think
我现在就两个字
I'm very happy.
快乐极了
Xiaoyu, let me help you.
小鱼那我也帮你一起
Hao, don't move.
小好姐 别动
You do the laundry all the time.
平时都是你在打扫
In the future, the activity
以后这种活动
is my duty.
交给我来吧
She's striving.
这听起来干劲十足
It seems that she's okay.
应该没啥事吧
I have been friends with her for ten years.
我认识她十年了
I can definitely tell you that
可以肯定地告诉你
she's not okay.
绝对不是
Let me tell you first.
先说好
The meal today
今天这一顿
is absolutely not a dismissal dinner.
绝对不是什么散伙饭
No matter we
咱们这一伙人
are members
无论以后
of the debate team
还是不是
of Dongzhou University of Finance and Economics,
东财大辩论队
the group will not be dismissed.
永远不散
The blue mountains never grow old.
青山不改
Friendship endures forever.
友谊长存
Cheer!
干杯
Come on!
来呀
What's this?
这什么
It tastes good.
还挺好喝的
The alcohol with a fruit taste also belongs to alcohol.
水果味的酒也是酒啊
It contains alcohol.
里面也有酒精
Don't be impulsive.
你悠着点
Don't worry. I know it.
放心吧 我有数
Shui, there's no water.
水哥 没有水了
Do you know
你知道人生最重要的
what is important in our life?
是什么吗
Striving and struggling.
努力 奋斗
Don't think that
你不要觉得
your life is bad now.
你人生现在过得很衰
When you are at my age,
当你到了我这个岁数
There's no water.
没有水了
you will think time flies
你会觉得光阴似箭
without pausing.
寸步不停
You don't have
你已经没有
the right to order.
点单的权利了
What are you saying?
你说什么
Pavel Korchagin
保尔·柯察金
once said that
曾经说过
She's drunk. Look after her.
喝多了 看一下
When you look back,
当你回首往事
you will not be ashamed of your lack of effort,
不因碌碌无为而羞耻
You continue saying.
你先说着啊
and regret for having wasted your time.
不因虚度年华而悔恨
How do you feel?
你怎么样啊
I send you back home.
我送你回去吧
I can't remember the rest.
后面我记不住了
I am not drunk.
我没喝多
Sa, make sure to
小撒 一定
take care of them.
你把她俩照顾好
I send her back home.
我把她送回去
I am not drunk.
我没喝多
Don't hold me up.
别扶我
You are going to reach the dormitory.
马上到宿舍了啊
Look.
你看啊
The tree in front of us
前面那棵树
is shaking.
它老晃
You go to hold it up.
你去扶它一下
I will stand steadily.
我站稳
I will hold it up.
我 扶它 扶它
I will hold it up after holding you up.
我先扶完你再扶它啊
Don't move.
别动
Let me lean on you.
靠一下
Nan Bei
南北
I was defeated by Yin Nan again.
我又输给了殷楠
Why do I say again?
为什么说又呢
Because from the childhood to the adulthood,
因为我从小到大
I have never defeated her.
就没有赢过她一次
Never.
一次都没有
It's okay. Never mind.
没事 没关系
But why was I
可是为什么
defeated in the debate?
连辩论也输了
I like debate the most.
我最喜欢辩论了
When we first met,
就咱俩刚认识那会儿
I only wanted to
我一门心思
be a member of the debate team.
想进辩论队
Then,
然后
I met you guys.
又认识了你们几个
We can
能每天
play together every day,
一起玩
prepare for the competition,
一起准备比赛
and win the competition.
一起打赢比赛
I'm so happy.
我好开心呀
Nan Bei
南北
There's no debate team any longer.
辩论队没了
Will we be separated?
我们是不是也会分开
What are you talking about?
说什么傻话呢
No matter there's a debate team or not,
不管辩论队在不在
I will be with you.
我都会一直陪着你
Xiaoyu, you are awake?
小鱼 你醒了
How did I come back?
我昨天怎么回来的
Nan Bei sent you back.
南北把你送回来的
For the first time,
我第一次看你
I witnessed that you drank so much.
喝这么多
I mean
我是说
Nan Bei is nice.
南北还挺亲切的
Right.
嗯嗯嗯
He is nice.
他是
Why are you so early?
你怎么这么快呀
I thought you would be late as well.
我以为你也得迟到呢
Which page?
第几页
Stand up. Let's switch the position.
起来 咱俩换个位置
Okay. The class is over.
好 下课啊
Follow me.
跟我走
Why are you walking so fast?
你走那么快干嘛呀
It's about the matter of last night.
关于昨晚的事
Last night?
昨晚
What's wrong?
怎么了
How do you think?
你怎么想
I don't want to mention it.
昨晚的事我不想说了
I don't think it's necessary to talk about it.
我觉得没什么可说的
Let it go.
该过去就让它过去吧
Let's pretend it didn't happen.
就当没有发生过
Okay.
好吧
That's all?
就这么点事
I am going to the dormitory if there's nothing.
那没事我回宿舍了
Sa
小撒
Come to my office.
来我办公室一下
Okay.
好嘞
Well.
嗯
This time,
这次啊
you can take it as a lesson.
就当是吸取教训
Actually, your team performed
其实你们队的表现
not badly.
也不算差
The condition before...
就是之前那种
The idle condition...
懒散的那种
Never mind.
算了 算了
I won't say that.
不说了 不说了
Don't be sad.
你也别难过啊
There is a matter.
有这么个事情
I need to tell you.
我跟你说一下啊
Okay.
哦
Do you remember
上一届的校队
the previous school team?
你还记得吧
Yes.
嗯
They took part in the provincial competition
他们呢 为了攒积分
to accumulate points.
参加省大赛
So, they repeatedly
所以说就来来回回
took part in these
参加这些
competitions which provide points.
攒积分的比赛
Finally,
结果呢
they almost failed.
差点栽跟头
Well.
嗯
But
但是呢
if your points are not enough,
你不攒够这个积分
you have no right to take part in the provincial competition.
就没法参加省大赛
Uh!
嗯
The final goal of
我们这个新校队呢
our new school team
最后的目标
is to win
就是要拿到
the champion of the provincial competition.
省大赛的冠军
So,
所以呢
they need
就要给他们
some time and energy.
留出一些时间和精力
The leaders of our school decided
这个校领导呢就决定
to organize a team two,
组织一个二队
which dedicates themselves to acquire points for them.
专门给他们打积分
Well.
噢
Who do you think
你觉得这个二队
is suitable for the team two?
谁合适啊
Well.
额
I have thought about that for a while.
我想了半天
I think your team is the most suitable one.
你们队最合适
What?
啊
Team two?
二 二队
Right.
对啊
Mr. Li, this is not suitable.
主任 这不太合适吧
Why is it not suitable?
怎么就不合适
This is a chance.
这是个机会啊
What?
啊
Don't think that leading the team two
你不要以为带二队
is embarrassing.
特别地丢脸啊
The team one has
军功章上
half of the merit.
有一队的一半
Your team two also has half of the merit.
也有你们二队的一半
Well, Mr. Li, this...
不是 主任 这
This is different.
这不一样吧
Psychologically, the kids...
孩子们心理他
So, I let you to
所以说让你去
persuade them.
好好地做工作
But...
可是
As for an intern,
你作为一个实习老师
this is a very good
这是一个非常非常好
chance to perform.
的表现机会啊
Well.
哦
Don't answer me in haste.
你不要着急回答我
I think it's suitable. There's no problem.
我觉得合适没有问题
Let me know when you've thought about it.
考虑好了你告诉我
Okay?
啊
Well.
那个
It's okay.
没问题
The next one.
下一个
Why is Xiaoyu so angry?
小鱼这是吃炮仗了吗
She's so fierce.
这么猛
This is abnormal.
这也太反常了
The more energetic she is,
她越是这么生龙活虎
the more I worry about her.
我越担心她
I have to deal with it.
不行 我得想想办法
To deal with it?
想想办法
Have a talk with her.
谈谈心呗
If we could persuade her,
我们要是能劝得动她
she wouldn't be like this today.
还至于她今天这样
Xiaoyu
小鱼
How about
一会儿我们一块
having a walk together later?
去散散心呗
I know there's
我知道这附近
a
开了一家
new dessert shop nearby.
新的甜品店
Call Tao Hao,
我们叫上陶好姐
and Nan Bei.
还有南北
Nan Bei
南北
Don't mention
别给我提那个
that scum.
人渣的名字
What did Nan Bei do?
南北怎么了
The next one.
下一个
We only sell drinks.
我们这儿只卖酒水
Food is not sold.
不卖吃的
Shui
水哥
If I don't save the kid,
我今天要不救这孩子
it will have to
它今天中午
be eaten at noon today.
就得祭五脏庙
Then it dies a worthy death, doesn't it?
那不是死得其所了吗
Have you ever heard of ducks bring back wealth?
你听说过鸭子招财吗
You can put one
只要把一只
drake into
公鸭放进一个
a room sitting in the north and facing the south,
坐南朝北的房间里
there will be many guests.
就可以招揽客源
The business is prospering.
生意兴隆
You will be rich in financial resources.
财源广进
It will bring more and more guests.
特别招客
Fine.
算了
As long as you promise
只要你答应我
to give me two deals every week,
每周给我两单生意
your son
你的儿子
is in the charge of me.
就交给我吧
That's nice of you.
够意思
Then I got to go.
那我撤了啊
You're really here!
你果然在这儿
What do you want from me?
找我有事
What's wrong with you and Xiaoyu?
你跟小鱼怎么了
It's no big deal.
没怎么呀
Last night,
你昨天晚上
you sent her back to the dormitory.
送她回宿舍
Was there anything special?
难道没有发生什么事
Nothing. It doesn't deserve to be mentioned.
没什么 不值得提
She's strange today.
她今天特别怪
She's angry with you.
对你怨气很深
She's angry with me?
对我怨气很深
Where is she?
她在哪儿啊
Well.
哎
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Why do you
你怎么看见我
hide when you see me?
就躲我啊
I come in to change my clothes.
我进来换衣服不行啊
I just finished my training.
我训练完了
Why are you always following me?
你老跟着我干嘛
I want to talk with you.
找你聊聊啊
According to Dango,
据团子同志所说
I seemed to annoy you.
我好像惹你生气了
I'm not annoyed.
我没有生气
I have nothing to
我跟你也没什么
talk to you.
可聊的
You go away.
你走吧
Actually, I know
其实我知道
the reason why you are annoyed.
你为什么生气了
Really?
真的
Yes.
嗯
After the dismissal of the debate team,
辩论队解散之后
we didn't
我们一直都没有
have a good conversation
好好聊过
about what to do in the future.
以后到底该怎么办
Maybe you think that
可能你觉得
I'm escaping the topic.
我在逃避这个话题吧
To be honest,
说实话
I'm a little bit.
是有点
People to some extent will
人多多少少都会对
be afraid to face
突如其来的改变
some sudden changes.
会有一些发怵吧
Xiaoyu
小鱼
Actually, I have figured it out.
其实我都想明白了
We stay together
我们聚在一起
because we have the common hobbies,
是因为共同的爱好
and the same values.
是因为三观一致
I also believe that
我也相信
in the future,
未来的日子里
you are in my life.
也肯定会有你们
Because for me,
因为对我来说
you are indispensable.
你们就是不可或缺的
You are an important part of my life.
很重要的一部分
Really?
真的
What I said comes from my heart.
发自肺腑
Well.
那
We should
那咱俩更应该
talk clearly about
把昨天晚上的事
what happened last night.
讲清楚了
Is that necessary?
真的有必要吗
This is my fault.
这事是我干得不对
But I was drunk.
但 我不是喝多了嘛
I don't want you to misunderstand me.
我不想你误会
So, what do you think?
所以你是怎么想的
Well.
那
I spent 1500 yuan buying them.
我一千五买的
You give me 800 yuan.
你算我八百吧
What?
啊
I tell you not to mention it.
我说要不就算了
There is no need
咱俩之间
to be so polite between us.
没有那么必要客气
We are good friends.
咱俩谁跟谁啊
I mean the thing last night.
我说昨天晚上
Right.
是啊
It's a matter of last night.
是昨天晚上的事啊
What a mess!
什么跟什么
The shoes.
鞋呀
Don't hold me up.
别扶我
Look.
你看呀
The tree in front of us
前面那棵树
is shaking.
它老晃
You go to hold it up.
你去扶它一下
I will stand steadily.
我站稳
Let me lean on you.
让我靠一会儿
Hello.
喂
Sa
小撒
Dango is back to the dormitory.
团子已经送到了
I...
我
Xiaoyu will be later
小鱼马上一会儿
back to the dormitory.
回去了
Nan Bei
南北
Okay, bye. See you later.
好 拜拜  一会儿见
I was defeated by Yin Nan again.
我又输给殷楠
Why do I say again?
我为什么要说又呢
Because I have never defeated her.
因为我总输给她
From the childhood to the adulthood, I
从小到大我
have never defeated her.
就没赢过她
I have never defeated her.
我没赢过她
But why was I
可是我为什么
defeated in the debate?
连辩论都输了
I like debate the most.
我最喜欢辩论了
When we first met...
咱俩刚认识那会儿
Nan Bei
南北
Do you think that
你说
after the dismissal of the debate team,
辩论队解散了
will we
我们是不是
be separated?
也会分开了
Nan Bei
南北
Oh, my god.
哎哟 我天
Let's go back to the dormitory. Let's go.
回宿舍了 走
Come on.
走走走
Don't shake me.
你别晃我
What's wrong with you?
你怎么了
I will try
我会试试
to wipe it out.
能不能把它擦干净
But it's impossible.
但估计悬了
I wanted to
我本来想着
let it go.
这事就这么过去了
Do you think that
你是不是觉得
I didn't take you as a friend?
我在跟你见外
Because I hope you to give me 800 yuan.
因为八百啊
It's cheap to cost you 800 yuan.
八百已经很便宜了
I tell you. The shoes are not the same with the cars.
我跟你说鞋不比车
The more I wear the shoes, the more expensive the shoes will be.
鞋越穿越贵
800 yuan is really...
八百已经真的很
It's good.
挺好的
800 yuan is good.
八百挺好的
Then, don't be annoyed.
那不生气了啊
I'm not annoyed.
我不生气啊
I'm refreshed and
我神清气爽
energetic.
充满干劲
Come on.
走
Come with me to practice boxing.
陪我再打轮拳
Okay.
好啊
Don't beat on my face later.
那别打脸啊 一会儿
Impossible.
不可能
Why do you suddenly
怎么突然说
plan to have a team two.
要组二队啊
Our school is going to take part in the provincial competition.
学校今年要打省大赛
It needs to obtain points in different places.
需要多校各地打比分
Our school wants to
想给校队
share the pressure.
分担一下压力
So...
所以就
They do not respect us.
太不尊重我们了
They can decide everything, right?
他们说什么是什么了
They asked us to dismiss the team. Then the team was dismissed.
他们说解散说解散
They asked us to be team two. Then should we organize the team two?
他们说二队说二队
I tell you.
我跟你讲啊
When I am in a room
把我和刘彦泽
with Liu Yanze,
放一屋里
either of us
迟早得有一个人
will go to meet the former couch.
去陪老教练
Well, I told that to Mr. Li.
是 我也是这么说的
If you do that like this,
你这事这么办
what should Dango do?
你让我们团子怎么办
What?
啊
Well.
哦
It's okay with me.
我没事
If you
大家如果
want to have the team two,
要是想去的话
I will agree with you.
我也没意见
Look.
你瞅瞅把我们
How embarrassed Dango is!
团子尴尬的
What?
啊
Will the two teams
那省大赛
fight with each other?
两个队一起打吗
He didn't tell me.
没有说
Maybe.
可能吧
That means it's impossible.
那就是不可能
Will it be possible for the team two
那二队有可能
to become the team one?
升为一队吗
He didn't tell me.
也没说
That's even more unlikely.
那更不可能了
Stop talking.
拉倒吧
Actually,
其实呢
I have
一开始我跟
the same attitude
大家的想法
with you at first.
是一样的
The team two
二队嘛
is an alternative.
备胎喽
We were once the team one.
我们曾经可是一队呀
How shameful a thing!
多丢脸的一个事
But,
不过
my friends,
朋友们大家好好
think about it.
想一想啊
Do we really care
我们真正在意的是
about the team one or the team two?
一队或者二队吗
No, we don't.
不是吧
What we really care about
那我们真正在意的
is debate.
是辩论这件事本身啊
We had
我们曾经为了
made a lot of efforts
保住我们的队伍
to keep our team.
做出过很多的努力
Now,
那么现在
there is a chance
就有这样一个机会
in front of us.
摆在我们面前了
My suggestion is
我建议大家
to think about it prudently.
还是慎重地考虑一下
How about this plan?
这样
You don't need to
大家也不用
answer me in haste.
着急回答我
I give you
我给大家
a week to think about it.
一个星期的时间
We decide it then.
到时候再说
Okay?
好不好